<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most excellent history of Antonius and Aurelia: or, The two incomparable lovers. Wherein is demonstrated the unparalel'd constancy of true affection to Aurelia by Antonius; the many inevitable dangers he underwent in the pursuit of her love; and how in the end he obtained it. Interlaced with pleasant discourses, wanton dalliances, and all the various intreagues which attend true love, when parents and friends are obstructive in the same. Very pleasant and delightful to read, especially to those whose mistrisses are perverse and froward, for hereby, observing the sequel of this history, they may by art and means obtain their desires.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51455</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826451</idno>
  <idno type="VID">30854</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240891678</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214248</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826451</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99826451e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1765:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most excellent history of Antonius and Aurelia: or, The two incomparable lovers. Wherein is demonstrated the unparalel'd constancy of true affection to Aurelia by Antonius; the many inevitable dangers he underwent in the pursuit of her love; and how in the end he obtained it. Interlaced with pleasant discourses, wanton dalliances, and all the various intreagues which attend true love, when parents and friends are obstructive in the same. Very pleasant and delightful to read, especially to those whose mistrisses are perverse and froward, for hereby, observing the sequel of this history, they may by art and means obtain their desires.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. Haley, and are to be sold by J. Wright, J. Clarke, W. Thackeray, and T. Passenger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:1"/>
            <p>THE MOST EXCELLENT HISTORY OF <hi rend="blackletterType">Antonius</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Aurelia:</hi> OR, <hi rend="italic">The two Incomparable Lovers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is demonstrated the unparalel'd Constancy of true Affection to <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> by <hi rend="italic">Antonius;</hi> the many Inevitable Dangers he underwent in the pursuit of her Love; and how in the end he obtained it.</p>
            <p>Interlaced with Pleasant Discourses, Wanton Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances, and all the Various Intreagues which attend true Love, when Parents and Friends are obstructive in the same.</p>
            <p>Very Pleasant and Delightful to Read, especially to those whose Mistrisses are Perverse and Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for hereby, observing the Sequel of this History, they may by Art and means obtain their Desires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi rend="italic">T. Haley,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi rend="italic">J. Wright, J. Clarke, W. Thackeray,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">T. Passenger.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="roman">THE Most Excellent HISTORY OF <hi rend="blackletterType">Antonius</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Aurelia:</hi> OR, <hi rend="italic">The Two Incomparable Lovers.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Antient times when the Tyrant <hi rend="roman">Vernon</hi> had V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped to himself the Government of the Kingdom of <hi rend="roman">Phrygia,</hi> by Murthering his Lawful Soveraign, and imbrewing his hands in the blood of faithful Subjects, there dwelt a certain Noble-man, named <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> who amongst many Temporal blessings which he enjoyed in abundant measure, he had one onely Daughter, named <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> the flower of that Age wherein she liv'd, forasmuch as she did far excell all others of her Sex, as well in the internal qualities and perfections of her mind, as the external feature and comeliness of her body, which was adorned with a most sweet carriage, and modest behaviour.</p>
            <p>There likewise dwelt some two Miles off, another Noble-man, by name <hi rend="roman">Esculenas,</hi> betwixt whom and <hi rend="roman">Aristeus</hi> there had been a great enmity for the space of many years, caused by the death of one <hi rend="roman">Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> a Gentleman that dwelt with <hi rend="roman">Esculenas,</hi> who was in a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel slain by some that did belong to <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> and such was the direful effect of that unhappy difference betwixt these two, that although many Friends sought often and diligently to find out some way whereby to Vnite them in a League of Friendship, yet nothing would prevail to make reconciliation betwixt them. <hi rend="roman">Esculenas</hi> had a Son named <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> whom he dearly loved, for he was every way deserving, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so dutiful to his Parents, so respectful to his Friends, so courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Strangers, so mild in his Speeches, so modest in his Carriage,
<pb facs="tcp:30854:3"/> so comely in Person, and every respect so outwardly accomplish'd, and inwardly qualified, that his Paralel was not to be found. Vpon a time it happened that <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> who delighted much in Hawking, was recreating himself in the fields so long, that he was even weary, wherefore being hot, and espying a pleasant Valley not far off, he walked thither with his Hawk on his fist, intending to repose himself a while in the shade.</p>
            <p>He was no sooner set down upon a green Bank, but presently a Pack of Hounds ran by open-mouth'd, being in full Chase after a Stagg, these Hounds did belong to <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> who with many of his friends did then pass by, riding swiftly after the Dogs: when they were gone a pritty distance from him, he sat down again to rest himself, but lifting up his eyes by chance to the top of the Hill, he espyed a fair Damosel leading her Horse down into the same Valley, whereupon he step'd aside into a private place, where he stood unseen, and there beheld the most vertuous <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> tying her Horse to a Tree, which being done, she laid her sweet body down upon the tender Grass, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced her Gown a little way to receive in the cool Ayr, the Weather being excessive hot, and she in a great sweat. <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> who beheld her all the while, thought she did not see him, took great delight in viewing her comely Person, noting well her admirable Beauty and rare Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, wherewith his heart was even ravish'd, but upon a sudden the Hawk stutter'd, and with the noise of his Bells made <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> start, and looking from whence the noise came she espyed <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> who lay upon the ground as one asleep, being not willing that she should have any knowledge of his seeing her, but she presently made all the haste she could to lace her Garment, and went towards her Horse, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ride away unseen; but <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> thought it not best to let her depart without speaking to her, therefore rising up, he went and thus saluted her: <hi rend="roman">Most Worthy Lady, let not, I beseech you, my Presence any way disquiet you, neither let my being a Stranger cause you to harbour any suspition of my harmless deportment, for I do assure you, I should think my self happy if with my poor ability I could be any way Serviceable unto you.</hi> She hearing his Speeches, made no reply at all, but mounting her Steed rode away, whereat he wondred that she made no Answer, but imputed her silence rather to her fearful disposition, then any discourtesie or want of Breeding.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:3"/>
            <p>Having lost the presence of so lovely an Object, he returned home, and after supper betook him to his Chamber, where he soon found a strange alteration; for, whereas he was wont to take his rest without any disturbance, now he could by no means drive out of his mind, the remembrance of that Lady which he had seen the day before: but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Cogitations silling his Heart, suffered him not to sleep at all, his sences being even captivated by her incomparable beauty, and his affections so enthralled, that he had quite lost all power and command over them.</p>
            <p>The next Morning he rose and got himself into the company of his dearest friends, in whose society he was accustomed to take greatest satisfaction, thinking thereby to drive quite out of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance those thoughts which had already procured him so much disquietness. But alas, it was in vain, for their discourse was now unsavory unto him, and he soon grew weary of their company, which heretofore was his delight to enjoy, such a change had one sight of <hi rend="roman">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relia</hi> wrought in him, that he seemed to himself to be quite another man, his friends endeavoured to drive him out of that Melancholly Posture, but could not prevail, which made them wonder what had happened unto him.</p>
            <p>Now it happened that a certain Knight named <hi rend="roman">Pegasius,</hi> with whom he was well acquainted, came and entreated his Company the next day, which he yearly solemnized as being his Birth-day, which request <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> promised to perform, and accordingly he went the next morning, where he was entertained amongst many Knights and Gentlemen, Ladies and Gentlewomen, with a sumptuous Feast and costly Banquet, which being over, the Graver sort of Men, with the Ladies and Gentlewomen, were seated upon a Scaffold erected for that purpose, to behold certain Sports; which were performed by the young Men, as well to exercise themselves and make proof of their Agility of Body, as to delight the eyes of the Spectators: <hi rend="roman">Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> though till then he never had made Tryal of his strength and skill in such Exercises, yet he behaved himself so gallantly, that he won the Praise from them all, and was presented to the Duke as Worthy of great Reward; this Duke was he, that out of love to <hi rend="roman">Pegasius,</hi> who had heretofore been his servant, was at the whole Charge of that Annual Solemnity: when the Sports were ended, and the spectators rising to depart, <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> casting up his eye by chance, he
<pb facs="tcp:30854:4"/> espyed <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> whom he very-well knew again by her favour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he desired of <hi rend="roman">Pegasius</hi> to know who she was; <hi rend="roman">Pegasius</hi> told him it was the Daughter of <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> who together with her Father and Mother, came that day to Honour him with their presence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> was somewhat comforted with beholding her, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that little knowledge of the place where she lived, yet he was much troubled at the Consideration of her being the Daughter of <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> who he well knew hated his Father, and in all probability would no ways approve of him, so that he was possessed with a mixture of fear and hope, revolving in his mind what a matter of difficulty it would be to gain her favour with such secresie as that it might not come to her Friends hearing, who he thought would never give their consent: sometimes again he thought it might be the readiest way to procure a reconciliation betwixt their two Families, yet because he knew <hi rend="roman">Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steus</hi> to be of a harsh stubborn nature, he feared that would not be effectual, neither so, that he was even ready to dispair of ever attaining to his desire; yet finding his affections to grow stronger, &amp; his love to encrease more and more, he resolved to put his intentions into practice and try his fortune by endeavouring to win her Love, and to that end, he rose early next morning, and walking towards the place where he had the first sight of <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> he met by the way an ancient Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman named <hi rend="roman">Milania,</hi> who was of good education, though but mean in Ability, she did very much frequent <hi rend="roman">Arbastus</hi> his house, and was then going thither: <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> seeing her alone, and not knowing but she might be a means of furthering his purpose, saluted her with these words: Mistris, if it be no offence or any way troublesome to you, I would demand of you one Question: Pray Sir (quoth she) without any further Apology, speak your Will, and I am ready to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie you in what I can: Do you (quoth he) know <hi rend="roman">Aristus?</hi> Yes that I do (quoth she) and am very well acquainted at his house, whether I am now going, so would I go too (said he) if I durst, for I belong to <hi rend="roman">Antonius,</hi> Son to <hi rend="roman">Esculenus,</hi> of whom I conceive you have heard, and might I receive your promise of secresie and fidelity, I would reveal a secret unto you, wherein you may I suppose, do my Master a great Courtesie, and be gratefully recompenced for your pains.</p>
            <p>Sir, (said she) I do not know <hi rend="roman">Antonius,</hi> but I have heard great Commendations of him, and if it lies in my power to do him any Service, I will not be wanting in my endeavours, but strive with
<pb facs="tcp:30854:4"/> the utmost of my ability to satisfie his Lawful requists, so having taken her Oath to be secret, he thus proceeded.</p>
            <p>It chanced that my Master sitting to rest himself in yonder Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, beheld the fair <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> by the sight of whose Beauty he was quite vanquished, and thorowly viewing her perfections, he became so enamored of her, that unless there be a speedy remedy found out to ease him of that trouble he undergoes, I fear it will cost him his life: you are the person that may do him a pleasure in revealing his love to <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> which I shall refer wholly to your managing, desiring you to effect the same in such a manner as by your prudence you shall be guided, and I know my Master will acknowledge himself much obliged to you for any pains you take in his behalf.</p>
            <p>Sir (said she) because I have some ground to believe that his Love is real, and his meaning Honourable, not having any sinister end in pretending that which indeed is not his intent, I shall therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my self to make known his humble suit to <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> and with the best of my skill strive to further the same, and if I cannot attain to my wish in working his contentment, I shall use as much secresie as can be desired or expected, and if you please to come to me to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row morning, you shall have an account of my proceedings, for which <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> gave her thanks and so departed. But when he was out of her sight, he began to accuse himself of too much Rashness, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting a matter of such great Importance to the privacy of a stranger, fearing lest <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> would not give Credit to his Speeches, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him as an Enemy, yet he did again comfort him elf with hopes of receiving encouragement by her favourable answer to his fuit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> being come to the Court, diligently watched her opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of gaining a fit time and occasion to speak to <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> and being in the Garden after dinner, they fell into discourse concerning the Names of several Herbs and Flowers; amongst which there was one which <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> said was call'd Love in Idleness, or Hearts-ease, at the uttering of which words <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> fetch'd a deep sigh which <hi rend="roman">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relia</hi> taking notice of, demanded of her why she sigh'd: Because (qd. she) there is such a vast difference between those two Names, that they are very unfitly given both to one Herb, and hereby, which is the cause of my sighing, I call to mind the great Lamentation which a Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man made in my hearing, whose sorrow was procured by Love, not in Idleness, but I think in good Earnest. Why (quoth <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi>) can
<pb facs="tcp:30854:5"/> Love be a means of such grief to any, and not rather of Ioy and Content? Yes, (quoth <hi rend="roman">melania</hi>) because the person loving hath little hopes of gaining the favour of her whom he so intirely loves. Then quoth <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> I account him very unadvised that will so deeply place his affections where there is such an unequality, as excludes him from all probabilty of having his Love answered with a return of the like again; but I pray tell me how came you to be admitted so quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the secrets of any Person? I was not admitted, quoth <hi rend="roman">Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lania,</hi> but chanced to hear his Complaints e're he was aware of me, which afterwards I promised not to make known to any, but the Lady whom he so dearly loveth: then it seems (quoth <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi>) I must not know, neither indeed do I care, for it is but a meer Vanity which disquieteth ones mind with distracting thoughts: Yes (quoth <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi>) you both may and shall if you please, know the party, so you will promise not to be displeased with me for telling you, nor yet reveal what I shall impart unto you: Why, quoth <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> I hope I am not so neerly concerned therein, as that I should be any whit offended: If I be I pray keep your secrets unrevealed, and trouble not me with such unrelishing discourse, for I am not disposed to give any Audience to the fond speeches of doting Lovers: truly quoth <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi>) in my judgement you give too harsh a censure of Love, which indeed is one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Quality, whereby a Man or Woman is distinguished from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures, and without which the world could not consist, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be disesteem'd, and if any one Love your self with a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous well-grounded Affection, should you make an ill construction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and not rather Answer it with kindness again, it being accounted a monstrous thing in Nature not to love them that love us, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Hatred for Love: you indeed are the Party beloved, and it is by one of whom I could say much, but I shall be silent in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and forbear to mention his Name, and then I hope your chaste Ears will not be offended with my Discourse.</p>
            <p>Do so then (quoth <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi>) and if hereafter you expect to be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come into my Company, forbear to utter any expressions of the like Nature: Had I thought (quoth she) this would have been any way unpleasing, I would not have used that priviledge which you gave me to speak what I knew, however for the future. I shall forbear, so they departed, <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> to her House, and <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> to her Lodging, where she began a little to muse of the discourse which had passed betwixt
<pb facs="tcp:30854:5"/> them, but passing over those thoughts slightly, she gave her self to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, and slept the greatest part of the Night very quietly.</p>
            <p>The next Morning very early, <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> repaired to <hi rend="roman">Melanias</hi> House, with a longing expectation of knowing what success his Suit had obtained, she was not up at his coming, but having intelligence that he was there, she quickly went down and acquainted him with all that had passed betwixt her and <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> whereat he was inwardly much perplexed, but she used many perswasions to keep him from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spairing of enjoying his wishes, though he had received such a strong repulse at first, giving him hopes, that in time her mind might alter from that which at present seemed to be her Resolution, for which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable hopes he return'd her thanks, and gave her a Purse full of Gold as a reward for the pains she had already taken, and to allure her to persist further in pleading for him, he said as followeth.</p>
            <p rend="roman">Good <hi rend="italic">Melania,</hi> let not <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi>'s first frown so dismay you, as that you should through fear desist from prosecuting my Suit, for I am not <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> man, but <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> himself, who endureth much sorrow, in that I am debared from the happiness of speaking to her my self in my own behalf, through the continual discord which is nourished by our Parents, therefore seeing I am destitute of any means or likelihood of pleading in my own Cause, I beseech you once more to make a further proof of your Skill, in speaking what you shall think most convenient to further my Suit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Sir, <hi rend="blackletterType">(said she)</hi> I would gladly put in practice any thing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Limits of my Power, thereby to purchase your content, but I fear that <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi>'s frowardness is such, that she will not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to any thing I say, though urged with never so much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, if it be not agreeable to her will, yet if you will be pleased to give me your advice what course is best to take, I will once more hazard the loss of her Friendship for your sake.</hi> Whereupon <hi rend="roman">An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> wrote a Letter, and desired her to convey it by some means or other to her sight, the Contents were as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="roman">
               <body>
                  <head>To the most Vertuous <hi rend="italic">Aurelia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SWeet Lady, let me not I beseech you, be condemned as guilty of too much rashness or boldness, in presuming to make this
<pb facs="tcp:30854:6"/> humble address unto you, but rather make a favourable constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my good meaning herein, for being bound to honour your vertuous self, I thought it most expedient to acquaint you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, desiring that you will by a kind entertainment of my Suit, ease me of that grief wherewith my heart is burthened through fear of your disdain, I must confess you may alledge many things, as Reasons to disswade you from believing the reality of my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, or affording me the least share of your favour, yet I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, make but tryal of my Loyalty, and you shall find the true heart of a constant friend, under the Veil of a supposed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; I am not able to express what a deep Impression your beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vertue hath made in my Breast, neither can I use any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which may be of more force to perswade you to give Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to my Speeches, then by entreating you to imploy me in your Service, and so to esteem of me as you shall by experience be sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmed in your good opinion of my faithfulness and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy, it lies in your power either to kill me, or prolong my life: Oh! let not Cruelty lodge within the Closet of your tender heart, but vouchsafe to pitty him, whose Safety, Comfort, and Preservation, consists in your owning him for your Servant, shew your favour to an undeserving, unknown friend, so shall you leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the days of a Languishing Lover, and oblige me to study all my life time how I may merit so great Honour as your kind acceptation of my Service will procure me, in hopes of receiving Encouragement by your Answer, I rest</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Devoted Servant, <hi rend="italic">Antonius.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> having received this Letter, promised it should be careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered, so the next day she went to <hi rend="roman">Aristeus</hi> house, and being with <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> in her Chamber, she espyed her Casken stand open, into which she conveyed the Letter, whilst <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> was imployed about o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther business, and softly shut the Lid down, making all the haste she could to be gone, for fear <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> should find the Letter whilst she was there: when Night was come, <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> being alone in her Bed, took a Book in her hand intending to read a while, but on a sudden she fell asleep, and was possest with a Dream, that <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> was using such Speeches as had the other day been spoken by her, at which <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> was very angry, and seemed in her sleep to chide <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> soundly, that
<pb facs="tcp:30854:6"/> she thereupon waked, wondring at her drowsiness, in that she had forgot to put out the Candle, and <hi rend="roman">Melanias</hi> Words concerning one that should so dearly love her, coming afresh into her mind, she mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled who it should be, yet desiring to think no more of it, she strove to free her mind from such Cogitations, but all her striving would not prevail, for the more she endeavoured to suppress those thoughts, the stronger they grew, whereupon laying aside her Book, she stept out of Bed to her Casket with intent to take her Sampler, and make use of her Needle, wherein she took much delight, but as soon as she had opened her Casket, she espyed the Letter, and admiring what should be the Contents, or how it should come there, she read the Superscription, and thought to look no further into it, but throw it away, which her heart would not suffer her to do till she had opened it to view the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, but striving to over-master her affections, she tare it in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, yet when she had done so, she was angry with her self that she had not first seen the Contents, therefore laying the two pieces toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before her, she read it all over, which being done, she uttered these Expressions: Ah me! what strange News is this? Was it <hi rend="roman">Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> that she spake of? can he pretend to be my friend, who is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt my professed Enemy? Can there be any good in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention towards me; no surely, it is some politick device of his to entreat me, thereby to work my Ruine: Was it he that saw me in the Valley? or is it probable that upon such a small sight he should be so far in love with me? No, I will never believe it, but still account him as my Enemy, and quite abandon <hi rend="roman">Melanias</hi> Company, whose device it was to put this Letter here: then tearing it in a hundred pieces, she would not yield to the least thought of Love, but forced as much as she could the remembrance thereof out of her mind, yet could she take little rest that Night, but spent many hours in various Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>When Morning was come she arose and soon met with <hi rend="roman">Melania,</hi> who came expecting to know what effect her Project had taken, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a sit opportunity when no body was there, she Schooled her in this manner: <hi rend="roman">Melania,</hi> I wonder what folly ruleth your mind, that leads you so far beyond the bounds of reason; I have not carried my self so unkindly towards you, as to merit such a requital of my Love, I always esteemed you to be a Person vertuously given, but I fear I have been mistaken, else you would never go about to undermine my
<pb facs="tcp:30854:7"/> Honour and betray it into the hands of such a person; I told you when we were talking in the Garden, that I would have you forbear to disquiet my mind with any such unsavory Language, which you then seriously promised to do, but have proved your self unfaithful in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to effect the same thing by a more secret and dangerous way, if your Immodesty would not permit you to desist from such unworthy undertakings, you might have given the Letter into my hand, and not under pretence of Friendship, sell me to one that intends nothing else but co intrap my Chastity, and procure my Misery, for I shall ever account him as my Enemy, and hereafter I pray come not into my Company, for i'le speak to my Father to forwarn you his House. <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> would have answered, but she went hastily away, refusing to hear her, whereupon being very much griev'd, she departed to her House.</p>
            <p>The next Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> repair'd to <hi rend="roman">Melanias</hi> House to hear what News, and finding her weeping for anger and vexation, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded how she had sped the day before, then she related unto him every passage and Circumstance of the whole matter, whereat he was struck to the heart with such a load of sorrow and grief, that without speaking one word he departed, and getting into a secret place, bewail'd with bitter sighs and tears, his lamentable estate, in being so unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate as to place so much Love upon one that was regardless of his Misery, and disdain'd his Suit, yet because he knew that he must either purchase her favour or lose his life, he resolved to make tryal of his skill in a further attempt, with hopes of better success.</p>
            <p>So resolving in his mind many things, and musing what should be the reason of her strangeness, in so utterly refusing to give credit to his words and protestations, he was at length verily perswaded that it was only his Name which procured her distrust of his good meaning, because thereby he was considered of in the quality of an Enemy, wherefore he concluded, that if he could find out a way to prefer his Suit under another Name, and in the likeness of another person, it were both possible and probable for him to attain his wishes, and hereupon with all the expedition that might be, he began to put his intended design in execution, and to that end, he attired himself in the habit of a Virgin come from a strange Country, and taking his Lure in his hand, on which he could play singular well, he repaired to the Sea-side in the Night time, unseen by any, and as soon as the
<pb facs="tcp:30854:7"/> light began to appear, next morning he sat him down on a Bank and plaid most sweetly on his Lute, which a poor old Shepherd that kept Sheep near that place chanced to hear, and admiring at the rarity of the Musick, he went to see from whence the Harmony came, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guided by the sound, he soon espyed <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> in the similitude of a Damosel newly come from some far Country; whilst he stood listen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Musick, and gazing upon him, <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> spake as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>Good Father, marvel not at such an unusual sight, for it seemed good to the fates, that being long tossed upon the Waves, after suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ship-wrack, I should be cast upon this shore alive, yet being far from any friends, and in an unknown Land, I am likely to perish here for want of comfort, being destitute of all means whereby to help my self, therefore I beseech you take pitty on my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> condition, and if it be in your power, yield me some relief, that my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be preserved; To whom the Shepherd replyed: Fair Damosel, such entertaiment as my poor Ability will afford, you shall be welcome to, and I shall be glad to do you any good that lies in my power, therefore I pray you walk with me to my House without any more entreaty, where you shall be kindly welcome. <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> gave him many thanks, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of his Courteous invitation, following him to his Cottage, where being entred, the Shepherd related to his Wife the Misfortunes of the Damosel, and what he had promised to do for her; whereupon the Woman had her welcome, and in a loving homely way expressed much kindness, setting before the supposed Virgin, such fare as was in the house, which <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> thankfully received, and being refreshed therewith, began to relate the reasons of his undertaking a Voyage by Sea, naming the place from whence he came, the Haven where he intended to Land, the dangers that he went through, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Ship-wrack he suffered, with many other strange passages which were so subtilly contrived, so seriously expressed, so positively affirmed, and so neatly shaddowed over with a Colour of seeming truth, that Persons of a far more discerning judgement, might have been easily perswaded to believe all was truth he said, and by reason of his Youth none could in that Habit mistrust his being any other than a young Virgin as he seemed; he told them moreover, that his Name was <hi rend="roman">Thalia,</hi> by which Name for a while we must call him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:8"/>
            <p>Having continued two days at the Shepherds House, without any likelihood of seeing <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> it chanced that upon the third day <hi rend="roman">Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steus</hi> as he rode a Hunting, was fortunately driven by a sudden storm, to seek shelter at the Shepherds house, where without any knocking, he boldly went in, and espying only <hi rend="roman">Thalia,</hi> he wondred very much to find a Damosel so Fair and so richly attir'd in such a poor Cottage, wherefore he thus Salutes her.</p>
            <p>Sweet Virgin, I beseech you excuse me if I have any way inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted you by my rash and sudden approach into your presence, for I little thought to have met so beautiful a Virgin in so homely a Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: <hi rend="roman">Thalia</hi> knowing him to be <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> arose from her seat, but answered not a word, immediately the Shepherd and his Wife came in, and with much reverence and submissive respect, expressed their gladness of being honoured with the presence of so worthy a Person as <hi rend="roman">Aristeus,</hi> the Shepherd relating unto him what he knew concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi rend="roman">Thalia,</hi> which caused <hi rend="roman">Aristeus</hi> to utter these Speeches.</p>
            <p>Fair Damosel, I understand by the Shepherds words that you have undergone great Misfortunes, which moves me to a Compassionate affection of your Sorrows, and I promise you I will do what lies in me to procure your content, and forasmuch as I suppose your breeding and education hath been so honourable, as that this homely Cottage is far unmeet to entertain you, I pray go home with me and receive such entertainment as my house affordeth, unto which you shall be freely Welcome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Thalia</hi> glad of the proffer, yet unwilling to give him any cause to suspect her by an overforwardness in accepting of his Courtesie, made this reply: Worthy Sir, I cannot tell how to acknowledge my self sufficiently thankful unto you for this undeserved favour, in vouchsafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such kindness to me, who am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> stranger and brought to Misery, wherefore I think this mean place is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uitable to my present low condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet because I am burthensome in these good people, and know not how to recompence their kindness already shewn me, and since you are pleased so far to condescend as to desire me to accept of your free prosfer, I do most willingly yield thereunto, and confess my self infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely obliged to you for your Love: Many the like Speeches past on either side, and at length <hi rend="roman">Thalia</hi> went with <hi rend="roman">Aristeus</hi> to his Castle, where he was kindly entertained, and by his sweet disposition and mild behaviour, he grew into favour with all the Houshold, <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30854:8"/> her self was so taken with his Carriage, that she much affected his Company, and he had his hearts desire in viewing the beauty, and enjoying the presence of <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> growing daily more enamoured of her, and taking such sweet delight in the Contemplation of her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine perfections, that no thoughts were pleasing to him but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of her.</p>
            <p>By this time the news of <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> sudden departure, was blazed abroad, and came to <hi rend="roman">Melanias</hi> ears, who hearing of the grievous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations his Parents made, fearing he was come to some untimely end; she carried the report to <hi rend="roman">Aristeus</hi> House, and entring the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den where <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> was walking with <hi rend="roman">Thalia,</hi> she could not forbear to express her mind, but spake as followeth</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> I entreat you not to take any distast at what I say, but if you will be angry, let it be with your self, who have been the cause of a Young-mans undoing, for <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> whom you esteemed as an Enemy, though a most trusty friend, and real Lover of yours, laying so to heart your disdainful refusal of his Suit, despaired of ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying any Comfort in this life, and therefore hath either made away himself, or else is gone to lead a solitary life in some strange place, far from the knowledge of his Parents, Friends, and Relations; how can you excuse your self from hard-heartedness, and too much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindness in procuring the misery of so Worthy a Gentleman, who was in all points so deserving, and whose Love was so Constant and Immoveable. Many the like expressions she used, which struck <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> into a dump that she knew not what to say, for she was by her own Conscience accused of too much Cruelty, and she could not in reason blame <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> who had spoken what was truth, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over she knew, that notwithstanding her own harsh Speeches before towards <hi rend="roman">Melania,</hi> there was some small sparks of Love kindled in her Breast, that could not well be concealed; as she stood musing thus betwixt hope and fear, the Water appeared in her eyes, being scarce able to contain her self from weeping, which exceedingly rejoyced <hi rend="roman">An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> his heart to see her begin to relent, and fain he would have spoken, but being in that disguise, he durst not reveal himself, lest it might be prejudicial to his design. <hi rend="roman">Melania</hi> having uttered her mind, and seeing <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> much perplexed, she her self also being extreamly grieved for the young-mans hard fortune, ceased to use any more words, but departed out of the Garden, and <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> withdrawing her
<pb facs="tcp:30854:9"/> self from <hi rend="roman">Thalia's</hi> Company into an Arbour, fell into a serious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of that which she had said and done in reference to <hi rend="roman">Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> sometimes blaming her self for giving such harsh Answers, and flat denials to his reasonable requests, other while fearing it might be a subtile device of <hi rend="roman">melanias</hi> on purpose to try her, but in the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, the expressions which proceeded from her tongue, did in a manner give certain testimonies that she in heart repented of what she had done, and gave <hi rend="roman">Antonius,</hi> who had hid himself secretly within hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her words, comfortable hopes of attaining her Love, but seeing her ready to rise up and come out of the Arbour, he soon conveyed himself into the place where she left him, where there past many words betwixt them; <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> supposing him to be what he seemed, no other then <hi rend="roman">Thalia</hi> a Virgin, began to explain more fully the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of such Speeches as <hi rend="roman">melania</hi> had used to her, relating the whole business concerning the Love which <hi rend="roman">Antonius</hi> professed towards her, and how she reputed him an Enemy only in this respect, because there was so great enmity betwixt their Parents, otherwise she had heard a good report of his Vertuous disposition, and rare Endowments wherewith Nature had adorned him; this pleased <hi rend="roman">Thalia</hi> exceedingly to hear, and sitting in a fine shady place, he took his Lute and plaid most sweetly; <hi rend="roman">Aurelia</hi> being much delighted with the Musick, so that when he gave over she would desire him to continue playing, which he did so long, that she fell into a slumber, and her eyes being closed, he took an occasion of viewing her matchless beauty, and exactly noted the most exquisite Composure of every visible part, wherewith her Person was so incomparably adorned; at length she awaking, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for his sweet Musick, which had much eased her mind by a quiet repose: and Night now drawing on, <hi rend="roman">Thalia</hi> was forced, though with much unwillingness, to lose the presence of <hi rend="roman">Aurelia,</hi> which was even as dear to him as his life: When he was alone by himself, he recounted in his mind those speeches which he had heard concerning himself, and was in a wilderness of doubts to what event things would come, sometimes fearing she was in hopes never to see her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, other while comforting himself with the remembrance of her sad complaint which she made against her self for affording him so much unkindness, in a disdainful repelling of his Suit, such a Labyrinth of perplexity did these contrarities of thoughts, of doubtful thoughts cast him, that he seemed as a Man round beset with sorrows, and
<pb facs="tcp:30854:9"/> destitute of all Comforts, uttering many sad and doleful complaints, bewailing his unhappiness, and lamenting his wretched estate; often did he think of making known himself unto her, but then again he fear'd lest thereby he should lose that priviledge which he now enjoyed in that disguise; at length overmastering his fears with the hopes of being pittied by her, he resolv'd to write his mind, and leave it in such a place where she might be sure to find it, then putting Pen to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he Wrote as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="roman">
               <body>
                  <head>To the most Incomparable Lady <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> the poor distressed <hi>Antonius</hi> Humbly presents these Breathings of his heart.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sweet Pearl of Beauty,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>CAn it enter into the belief of any, that cruelty lodgeth in your tender Breast, or that your heart, the sole harbourer of all vertuous qualities, should be destitute of pitty? Ah! no, I will never cease to extol your Fame, wholly laying the blame up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my unhappy Fates, who envying my felicity, to deprive me of any hopes of comfort, have defamed me with the false Title of an Enemy, but the Heavens can witness my Loyalty, and with what vehemency of desires my heart longeth to evidence my love and duty, which I have devoted to your sacred person, I cannot fix credence to my words, nor paint over flattering speeches with such colours as bear the resemblance of truth, but I do unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly protest, that my love is vertuous, constant, and imoveable; not to be extinguished by disdain, not to be altered by distance of place, nor worn out of remembrance by continuance of time: I beseech you therefore, shew some compassionate kindness to him that waits to receive the sentence of life or death from your lips, let mercy take place, and save me alive: So shall you gain a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant who will study all his life time to requite your favour: I have forsaken my Parents and Friends, only to purchase your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of my Service: When I was <hi rend="italic">Esculenus</hi> Son, I was despised and accounted your enemy, but now I am not <hi rend="italic">Esculenus</hi> Son, nor <hi rend="italic">Antonius,</hi> let me obtain favour at your hands; So shall you restore me to a ioyful and happy estate, and by your pitty in preserving my life, eternize your own memory to all posterity: Thus, with the tender of my true respects unto you, I commit my Cause wherein my safety depends, to your wise Consideration:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, or not his own, <hi rend="italic">Antonius.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:10"/>
            <p>When he had thus written, he sealed it up and laid it in the Garden, in a Walk to which <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> daily repair'd, and going to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he found her ready to come down; after she had welcomed <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> her supposed Gentlewoman, she went with her into the Garden, where walking a while, <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> espyed the white Paper, which she took up, and reading the Superscription, marvelled from whom it came, or who laid it there; then calling <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> unto her, she said, Do you see this? I wonder how it came hither, or what the Contents may be; it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to me, and therefore I will open and read it, and you shall hear the same as well as I; when she had perused it quite over, and saw that it was from <hi rend="italic">Antonius,</hi> she fetched a deep sigh, saying, now I perceive <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> was not so void of reason and wisdom as to make away himself, but will make a further tryal of me, e're he will give over his Suit for labour lost; this I dare say was <hi rend="italic">Melanias</hi> doings, I perceive they are agreed, well my mind is much troubled, I prethee <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> let me have thy advice what is best for me to do, for I will resolve upon nothing till I know thy judgement concerning the thing, to whom <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> replyed; Madam, since you are pleased to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> favourable opinion of me, as to conceive my Counsel may be available unto you, and have given me free liberty to express my thoughts, I shall briefly tell you what I think: first, If <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> doth so really Honour Love, and Respect you as he protesteth, you have all the reason in the world to entertain his Suit, and recall yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> harsh censure, for thereby you shall not only save his Life and purchase to your self a sure Friend, but also procure a perpetual reconciliation betwixt your two Families; secondly, For <hi rend="italic">Melania,</hi> she did but a friendly part if it were of her doing, which I hardly believe▪ because she was not here since yesterday: Again, in my opinion all the speeches and expressions of <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> seem to proceed from the very bottom of his heart, so that I am perswaded all his vows and protestations are real, and free from Dssimulation and Falshood. Therefore, if I may advise you, so far as you may be assured of his vertuous and honourable meaning, yield to his requests, and release him from that thraldome wherein he lies languishing, which will be a deed of true pitty.</p>
            <p>Would you, quoth <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> have me consent to love mine enemy? How can he be your Enemy, said <hi rend="italic">Thalia,</hi> when he so dearly loveth you? you have no other reason in calling him so, but the discord betwixt your Parents, which hinders not the Children in the least from bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:30854:10"/> true affection one to another: and further, here is an evident proof of his vertuous inclination, in as much as because he knows you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be beloved, he therefore will love you though his Parents hate you: Many the like powerful arguments <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> used to prove the certainty of <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> love towards her, and to move her to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain favourable constructions of his good meaning, whereupon <hi rend="italic">Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> seeing how like a Counsellor she pleaded in his cause, said as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: Indeed <hi rend="italic">Thalia, Antonius</hi> hath a good Oratour to speak for him in his absence, I asked thy advice and thou hast therewith joyned perswasion, but seeing thou art so desirous of my good, which I hope is the end thou aimest at, if thou wilt promise secresie, I will acquaint you with my mind and intentions; you may rest assured (quoth <hi rend="italic">Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>) that I will be faithful unto you in whatsoever you entrust me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: then said she) I confess unto thee, that I do both love <hi rend="italic">Antonius,</hi> and am desirous to grant his requests, but I fear there will be so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impediments and obstacles in the way, that I shall never enjoy him, for should my Parents have the least inclination of such a thing, they would be so strict in watching over me, that I fear I shall scarce attain to one sight of him whom I greatly long to see. Never fear, (quoth <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi>) but you may both see and enjoy him, for you loving him, and he not only equalling, but exceeding you in affection, the business will more easily be effected, and could I but come once to the Speech of him, I question not but I should with secresie and sincerity procure both your contentments; well then (said <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi>) putting sure confidence in thy fidelity, and not in the least distrusting thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness, I commit my love, my life, and all to thy Prudence, being willing to follow thy directions in yielding to any thing that may not impair my honour, or be inconsistent with vertue: When they had ended their discourse, being ready to depart, <hi rend="italic">Melania</hi> entred the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, whereupon <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> began presently to chide her, using sharp ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, &amp; accusing her of dissimulation, also taxing her with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of that Letter into the Garden, and of being privy to <hi rend="italic">Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> departure, whom she conceived did privately lodge at her house; <hi rend="italic">Melania</hi> extreamly marvelled to hear such speeches, and did with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn protestations avouch her ignorance of those things which <hi rend="italic">Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> laid to her charge, affirming that she had not seen <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> since he came to know what success the Letter had which she conveyed into her Casket, adding further, that she fear'd it was not so well with him
<pb facs="tcp:30854:11"/> as to be so near at hand; <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> hearing her speeches, gave credit to her protestations, and could not contain her self from shedding some tears, which serv'd only to usher in a far greater showre of rain, for at that instant one of the Servants came running in all post hast to <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> telling her in doleful words, a sad Tragical Story, how that her Father riding out that morning a Hunting, was on a sudden mist, whereupon his men riding several ways in search of him, at length he was found in a Wood hard by grievously wounded and dead, at which words she fell down in a swound, ready to give up the Ghost, but <hi rend="italic">Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> took her up in his arms, rubbing her pale Cheeks till she began to revive again, then they convey'd her to bed, but she was brought by the extreamity of her grief into such an Agony, that it was fear'd she would scarce ever recover her health again, which fill'd <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> with sorrow and inward perplexity; the whole house at this sudden news was presently in an uproar, wailing and lamenting <hi rend="italic">Aristeus</hi> death, every one giving their opinion concerning the murther, and it was generally conceiv'd, that it was done by the procurement of <hi rend="italic">Esculenus</hi> in revenge of his brothers death. <hi rend="italic">Aristeus</hi> Wife laid the loss of her dear husband so to heart, that within few days she dyed. <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise had followed them both, had she not been carefully and diligently tended by <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Melania,</hi> by whose assistance and counsel she was preserved alive: the report of this strange accident was quickly noised abroad all about the Country, but there being no certain knowledge of the murtherer, it past unquestioned: <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> began now to take possession of his Brothers Lands and Livings, and having honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly buried him and his Lady, he erected stately Monuments in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, often visiting <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> and with kind expressions of his tenderness towards her, he seemed to be studious of her welfare, and did often promise he would be unto her in the stead of a Father, giving order to her attendants, that she should want nothing which might any way conduce to her speedy recovery from that sorrowful sickness which seiz'd upon her, and whereby she was brought into such a weak estate. <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> was not a little grieved to see his Love in that condition, yet it was some comfort that he had the priviledge of being contiually with her never departing out of her Chamber day nor night, but taking pains and using his utmost diligence to pleasure her, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he grew in such esteem with her, that she took much delight in his company, still supposing him to be a Virgin as he seem'd; <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30854:11"/> would oftentimes steal a sweet kiss from <hi rend="italic">Aurelias</hi> Lips, which she thought was out of extraordinary kindness, and took it in good part: but being somewhat recovered, she marvelled <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> would so often get into some secret place, and there bewail his condition with heavy sighs, and doleful lamentations: one time above the rest, <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> chanced to hear him say; Oh how great misery do I endure, in placing my affections on one that repays my love with disdain: more he was about to say, but espying her he ceased: whereupon <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> spake as followeth: Why how now <hi rend="italic">Thalia,</hi> are pou bitten by that poysonous Serpent Love, that enemy to tranquillity and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? which disquiets the mind, changeth the complexion, troubleth the head and heart, and disturbs all the senses: sie, sie, shake it off quickly, lest it bring you into such a Labyrinth of sorrow as you will never be able to get out of it: To which words of hers <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> made this answer: Madam, I should wrong my self if I should say I were not in love, yet I le assure you that hath wrought in me no such strange effects as you speak of, but I have enjoyed much felicity the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and all my sences have been exceedingly rejoyced thereby: How comes it then to pass (said <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi>) that you sit in such a melancholly posture, as if you did lament your being in Love? It doth not trouble me at all (qd. <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi>) that I am in love, but I am not beloved again, for I have resolved to persist in loving so long as I live. What Man can be so void of pitty (said <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi>) that knowing you love him, will not vouchsafe you love again? 'Tis indeed strange (qd. <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi>) but truly thus the case stands with me, the person whom I love knoweth it very well, and yet disdains, and even hates me without any just cause: neither am I far distant from my Beloveds company, which is the only support of my life. It should then seem by your talk (said <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi>) that the party you love is in this house, is it possible your fancy should be so quickly ensnared, and your heart captivated in the short space you have been here: Pray, if you dare conside in my secresie, make me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the party, and I will do what lies in my power to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your love. I most humbly thank you (qd. <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi>) and you may do more therein then any other can: yet with your pardon, before I reveal my mind, I would crave leave to ask you one question. Name it (quoth she) and I will answer you. I desire, qd. <hi rend="italic">Thalia,</hi> to know whether you love <hi rend="italic">Antonius,</hi> yea or no? Love <hi rend="italic">Antonius,</hi> said she, ah woe is me, that very name cuts me to the heart, dost thou think I have
<pb facs="tcp:30854:12"/> reason to love him, and not rather to hate him above all others? who hath brought me to this misery, for without question it was either he, or some other imployed by him, that murthered my Father, therefore I do hate and abhor the very remembrance of him, his very name terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies me, and if thou hadst loved me as I thought thou didst, thou wouldst have forborn to mention it. Yet to see the villany and perjury of base Men, how did he with feigned protestations sue for my love, and had gone so far that my heart began to give consent to his requests, which would have proved my utter ruine if he had attained his ends. <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> was so fully possest with grief to hear these speeches, that she burst forth into tears, and being about to speak, was prevented by <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> coming to visit <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> who as his custom was, abounded in loving expressions, and pretended kindness, protesting to be as desirous of her welfare as his own good, advising her not to let immoderate grief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in her heart, which would be a means to prolong her Malady, but that she would be chearful, as heretofore she us'd to be: after many speeches to this purpose, they departed, and at night when <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> was alone, he call'd to mind <hi rend="italic">Aurelias</hi> Words, which put him into an utter despair of ever obtaining his desires, all the comfort which he had left him was, that he might enjoy the sight and presence of his beloved Lady. In this condition and disguise continued he till <hi rend="italic">Aristeus</hi> death was almost worn out of memory, in which time <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> began to affect <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> the supposed Damosel, and by degrees fell so deep in love, that he could no longer conceal it: whereupon he took occasion to acquaint her therewith, and desired that she would grant him her favour. <hi rend="italic">Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> laughing in himself at the conceit, and well considering that such a project might further him in his love to <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> gave him such ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers as encouraged him to continue his suit; not making him a full grant of her love, but holding him in dispence to get what she could out of him: and being possest with thoughts, coming as it were by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary providence into her mind, that <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> might be privy to the murther of his brother <hi rend="italic">Aristeus,</hi> she intended to sift him through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that if it were possible the truth of all might be found out, and to that end, when he continued his importunity in urging her to give him some promise of her love, she would still alledge his want of means &amp; ability to maintain her, telling him the estate which he possest belonged to <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> and that he could not claim it as his inheritance, putting him off with such delays the better to bring her purpose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout:
<pb facs="tcp:30854:12"/> which enflamed his heart more exceedingly, &amp; thinking that it he could get that obstable removed out of the way, that is to say, his want of wealth, then he should quickly obtain his desire; and being hardned in mischief, he resolved to attempt any thing that might further him in his unlawful enterprize. Therefore coming to <hi rend="italic">Thalia,</hi> and using many pressing arguments to move her to yield to his demands, which she feignedly seemed willing to consent unto, if he could assure her of any wealth he had of his own: he told her that he had a secret to impart unto her, which if she would swear to conceal, he would make her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it. She protested that she would faithfully conceal what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he should say: Then he opened his mind, telling her that he had an intent to make away <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> by removing her to a private Lodge in her Fathers Park, pretending her health therein, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might easily be effected, if she would take the performance in hand, for he would order her to attend continually upon her, and he would provide such a drink that she should give <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> that would suddenly dispatch her, and none could never know but that she dyed of some Natural Dist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> trembling to hear this Tragical story design'd against the welfare of his dearest <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> was ready to sink down, but dissembling his grief, told <hi rend="italic">Duratus,</hi> who took her to be <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> indeed, that she supposed he did not mean to perform any thing he had said, but spake it only to try her disposition, and to ensnare her, which he vow'd was not fo, but wisht heavy Curses might light upon him, if it were not his full intent; and further to assure her thereof, he told her that it was he that kill'd <hi rend="italic">Aristeus,</hi> though it was laid to the charge of <hi rend="italic">Escu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenus</hi> Family; <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> having now as much as she desired, promised him to perform his will, and fulfill his purpose in every point, which he believing, departed: the next day <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> came with flattering speeches to <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> and making a large Narration of his great care, study, and desire of her welfare, he acquainted her that he thought it would be very expedient for her bodily health, to remove into the fresh ayr, and remain for some space in the Lodge, which should be prepared to entertain her, and nothing should be wanting to accomodate her while she staid; she nothing mistrusting his villanious intentions, gave him thanks, and promised to take his Counsel: when the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time was come, she was conveyed to the Lodge, having onely <hi rend="italic">Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> with her, who knowing it now to be high time to disclose the
<pb facs="tcp:30854:13"/> whole business, and having so convenient an opportunity, he declared all that <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> had said and done, with his purpose in sending her thither to be poyson'd, having by his own confession acknowledged himself the Author of <hi rend="italic">Aristeus</hi> death: this did exceedingly amaze <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> not knowing whether she might give credit to the words of her supposed <hi rend="italic">Thalia,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> to put her out of all doubt, revealed himself, and gave her assurance that he was <hi rend="italic">Antonius,</hi> who destitute of all other means, had undertaken that hazard to purchase her favour, which then she could not but grant, knowing that he had abundantly deserved her love; so changing her former opinion concerning him, as being a Foe, and receiving him now as the only preserver of her life, she committed her self wholly to his protection, her heart being firmly united unto him in the hands of inseparable affection: three days after <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> came and brought the glass of Poyson, which he delivered to <hi rend="italic">Thalia</hi> desiring her to give it <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> the next morning, which he promised to do, but was far from having any such intent, for he gently conveyed <hi rend="italic">Aurelia</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Melanias</hi> house, where she continued secure, till within a short space the Murther was miraculously found out, and <hi rend="italic">Duratus</hi> being by his own confession, the only actor thereof, was Condemned to be Hang'd, Drawn, and Quartered; after the Execution of which Sentence upon him, <hi rend="italic">Antonius</hi> was with great Solemnity Married to <hi rend="italic">Aurelia,</hi> spending the remainder of their days in perfect Vnity and Tranquillity, by which means they procured an inseparable and perpetual League of Friendship between their two Families.</p>
            <trailer>
               <hi rend="italic">FINIS.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30854:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>